BETH: Sometimes the challenging behaviour
of an individual with autism can become
so great that the family will need to
seek external support of specialists
to help and there are many different
sources of help and support available.
If the distressed behaviour of a
child or family member presents a
significant risk to themselves or those
around them, specialist help should be
sought out to deal with the behaviour.
JOE: They could request a social care
needs assessment for their family
member and for themselves as a carer.
They may be able to get respite care
or the help of an outreach team who can
support them with behaviour strategies.
Discussing this with a GP and
requesting a referral to a behavioural
specialist may be appropriate.
Getting support from a counsellor who
understands autism and can support
the individual and their family.
BETH: There are a number of ways
in which a parent/carer can get
support such as meeting up with other
carers, getting ideas from other
families, and swapping tips in online
communities nationally or locally.
They could try contacting a
local ‘National Autistic Society’
group, community service or family
support service in their area.
JOE: The ‘Challenging Behaviour
Foundation' has a lot of information
to help both parents and professionals
to give support and advice on
spotting behaviours that challenge
and what to do when it occurs.
‘Scope' also has information for
parents on challenging behaviour.
Families should not suffer in silence
as there is help out there and help
and support will make life better
for all concerned in the long run.